<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<texts>
    <TextEngineInfo xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:type="textEngineInfo">
        <id>1</id>
        <intensity>0.17363778</intensity>
        <negativeGroup>divisive; fifteen; damaging; permanent; four; beginning; two; six; retiring; this; less; controversial; several; individual; once; following; africa; add; three; only; five; accountable; one; may; avoid; twenty; america; immediate; each; few; </negativeGroup>
        <polarity>POSITIVE</polarity>
        <positiveGroup>flexibility; ensure; serve; open; such; restraint; objective; call for; kingdom; competitive; formal; region; information; general; initiative; larger; text; great; eligible; fair; article; clear; council; security; group; member; contribution; american; major; flexible; represent; according; aspiring; membership; sit; continue; entail; republic; asian; united nations; length; social; first; country; increase; democratic; effective; due; allocation; election; worthy; term; rotation; identify; including; agreement; amend; determined; effort; have; international; rock; transparency; long; representative; affirmative; address; all; new; initial; matter; wanted; set aside; single; implement; assembly; permit; achieve; entitled; different; peace; over; balance; granting; proposal; addition; decide; contentious; draft; being; interested; participation; for; union; conducive; submit; require; better; western; additional; consensus; approach; create new; past; elect; circle; cooperation; circulation; adequate; exchange; left; subject; maintenance; majority; paragraph; question; regard; performance; environment; make; access; best; decision; interaction; remote; use; community; recommend; purpose; resolution; economic; vote; broad; meaningful; inclusive; possible; special; </positiveGroup>
        <text>The Security Council would consist of 20 elected members, serving for a two-year term, in addition to the five permanent members, according to a draft resolution presented to the General Assembly this afternoon.
By other terms of the text (document A/59/L.68), co-sponsored by the 12-strong group of Member States known as Uniting for Consensus, the Assembly would also make amendments to the United Nations Charter and submit them for ratification by Member States.  According to the text, the amended Article 23, paragraphs 1 and 2 of the Charter, would read, as follows:
“1.  The Security Council shall consist of twenty-five Members of the United Nations.  France, the People’s Republic of China, the Russian Federation, the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and the United States of America shall be permanent members of the Security Council.  The General Assembly shall elect twenty other members of the United Nations to be non-permanent members of the Security Council, due regard being specially paid, in the first instance, to the contribution of Members of the United Nations to the maintenance of international peace and security and to the other purposes of the Organization, and also to equitable geographical distribution.
“2.  The non-permanent members of the Security Council shall be elected for a term of two years.  In the first election of the non-permanent members after the increase of the membership of the Security Council from fifteen to twenty-five, five of the retiring members shall continue for one more year.  Non-permanent members may be eligible for immediate re-election, subject to the decision of their respective regional groups.”
Further by the text, the Assembly would also amend Article 27, paragraphs 2 and 3, and Article 109, paragraph 1, of the Charter to require the affirmative vote of 15 of the 25 Council members.  The Assembly would also call for improving the Council’s working methods in a transparent, inclusive and accountable manner, including restraint on the use of the veto; procedures to ensure transparency in decision-making, accountability in performance and access to information, including open briefings and interaction with all interested parties; consultation, cooperation and adequate exchange of information with the General Assembly and the Economic and Social Council; access and better participation of non-member States of the Security Council in its work; and the adoption and circulation of formal rules of procedure.


According to the text, presented to the Assembly by the representatives of four Uniting for Consensus members -- Canada, Italy, Colombia and Pakistan -- the Assembly would decide that the 20 non-permanent members of the Security Council would be elected according to the following pattern:  six from African States; five from Asian States; four from Latin American and Caribbean States; three from Western European and Other States; and two from Eastern European States.
The proposal would have the Assembly recommend that each geographical group decide on arrangements among its members for re-election or rotation of its members on the seats allotted to it.  Those arrangements would also address a fair subregional representation.
Other members and co-sponsors of the text, entitled “Reform of the Security Council”, are Argentina, Costa Rica, Malta, Mexico, Republic of Korea, San Marino, Spain and Turkey.
The text was introduced following discussions over the past two weeks on several competing proposals for Security Council reform.  The proposal by the “Group of Four” (G-4) -- Brazil, Germany, India and Japan, all of whom are aspiring to become permanent members of the Council -- would have the Assembly increase the Council’s membership from 15 to 25, by adding six permanent and four non-permanent members.
Another initiative considered by the Assembly was the African Union proposal, which would increase the body’s membership from 15 to 26, with increases in both the permanent and non-permanent categories, and granting Africa two permanent and five non-permanent seats.


Introduction of Draft

ALLAN ROCK (Canada), introducing the draft (document A/59/L.68), said that the objective of the text was to achieve the fairest and most democratic approach to the complex and controversial question of Security Council enlargement, while seeking the broadest possible consensus on how to proceed.  It would not serve the larger purpose if nations were left divided after choosing among resolutions that favoured a few, leaving fissures and factions as winners and losers were picked, once and for all.
The draft before the Assembly represented a good-faith effort to avoid such an “all or nothing” approach, he said.  It would add no permanent members to the Council, but would rather create new permanent seats in each region, leaving it to the members of each regional group to decide which Member States should sit in those seats, and for how long.  That approach would permit the international community to achieve all of the major objectives of Security Council reform, while preserving an environment conducive to broad agreement in September, and cooperation in the years ahead.
The accession of additional permanent members to the Council was not in the best interests of the United Nations, and it was not in the best interests of the overwhelming majority of its Member States, he continued.  Widening the permanent circle for the few who sought special status, no matter how worthy their candidacies, would make the Council less accountable for its conduct, more remote from the membership and less representative of the world’s regions.
His country favoured the approach presented in the draft, because it was democratic; it would make the Council more accountable to Member States; it provided for a flexible allocation of Council seats; and it provided for fairness.  And finally, it provided for a meaningful and effective Council reform without forcing divisive and potentially damaging votes on the General Assembly, as individual States vied for special status.
One of the aspects of the draft’s flexibility was that it allowed for repeated terms of different aggregate length among the elected seats permanently allocated to each region.  For example, it permanently accorded Africa six seats on the Council.  The African Group had made it clear that it wanted to have two representatives on the Council, who would be there for the long term.  The draft empowered the Group to identify two of its members who would represent the region for as long as that Group decided.  The balance of the seats set aside for Africa could be held for periods to be determined by the region.
Each of the other resolutions before the Assembly provided for new permanent members of the Council, but if either of those drafts were to be adopted, that would be only the beginning of a contentious and competitive process.  The approach of L.68 would entail a single initial vote of the Assembly, with subsequent elections that would implement the choices of regional groups.</text>
    </TextEngineInfo>
    <TextEngineInfo xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:type="textEngineInfo">
        <id>2</id>
        <intensity>0.17363778</intensity>
        <negativeGroup>divisive; fifteen; damaging; permanent; four; beginning; two; six; retiring; this; less; controversial; several; individual; once; following; africa; add; three; only; five; accountable; one; may; avoid; twenty; america; immediate; each; few; </negativeGroup>
        <polarity>POSITIVE</polarity>
        <positiveGroup>flexibility; ensure; serve; open; such; restraint; objective; call for; kingdom; competitive; formal; region; information; general; initiative; larger; text; great; eligible; fair; clear; article; council; security; group; member; contribution; american; major; flexible; represent; according; aspiring; membership; sit; continue; entail; asian; republic; united nations; length; social; first; country; increase; democratic; effective; due; allocation; election; worthy; term; rotation; identify; including; agreement; determined; amend; effort; have; international; rock; long; transparency; representative; affirmative; address; all; new; initial; wanted; matter; set aside; single; implement; permit; assembly; achieve; different; entitled; over; peace; balance; granting; proposal; addition; decide; contentious; interested; participation; being; draft; union; for; conducive; submit; require; better; western; additional; consensus; approach; create new; past; elect; circle; cooperation; circulation; adequate; exchange; left; subject; maintenance; majority; question; paragraph; regard; performance; environment; make; access; best; decision; interaction; remote; use; community; purpose; recommend; resolution; economic; meaningful; broad; vote; inclusive; possible; special; </positiveGroup>
        <text>The Security Council would consist of 20 elected members, serving for a two-year term, in addition to the five permanent members, according to a draft resolution presented to the General Assembly this afternoon.
By other terms of the text (document A/59/L.68), co-sponsored by the 12-strong group of Member States known as Uniting for Consensus, the Assembly would also make amendments to the United Nations Charter and submit them for ratification by Member States.  According to the text, the amended Article 23, paragraphs 1 and 2 of the Charter, would read, as follows:
“1.  The Security Council shall consist of twenty-five Members of the United Nations.  France, the People’s Republic of China, the Russian Federation, the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and the United States of America shall be permanent members of the Security Council.  The General Assembly shall elect twenty other members of the United Nations to be non-permanent members of the Security Council, due regard being specially paid, in the first instance, to the contribution of Members of the United Nations to the maintenance of international peace and security and to the other purposes of the Organization, and also to equitable geographical distribution.
“2.  The non-permanent members of the Security Council shall be elected for a term of two years.  In the first election of the non-permanent members after the increase of the membership of the Security Council from fifteen to twenty-five, five of the retiring members shall continue for one more year.  Non-permanent members may be eligible for immediate re-election, subject to the decision of their respective regional groups.”
Further by the text, the Assembly would also amend Article 27, paragraphs 2 and 3, and Article 109, paragraph 1, of the Charter to require the affirmative vote of 15 of the 25 Council members.  The Assembly would also call for improving the Council’s working methods in a transparent, inclusive and accountable manner, including restraint on the use of the veto; procedures to ensure transparency in decision-making, accountability in performance and access to information, including open briefings and interaction with all interested parties; consultation, cooperation and adequate exchange of information with the General Assembly and the Economic and Social Council; access and better participation of non-member States of the Security Council in its work; and the adoption and circulation of formal rules of procedure.


According to the text, presented to the Assembly by the representatives of four Uniting for Consensus members -- Canada, Italy, Colombia and Pakistan -- the Assembly would decide that the 20 non-permanent members of the Security Council would be elected according to the following pattern:  six from African States; five from Asian States; four from Latin American and Caribbean States; three from Western European and Other States; and two from Eastern European States.
The proposal would have the Assembly recommend that each geographical group decide on arrangements among its members for re-election or rotation of its members on the seats allotted to it.  Those arrangements would also address a fair subregional representation.
Other members and co-sponsors of the text, entitled “Reform of the Security Council”, are Argentina, Costa Rica, Malta, Mexico, Republic of Korea, San Marino, Spain and Turkey.
The text was introduced following discussions over the past two weeks on several competing proposals for Security Council reform.  The proposal by the “Group of Four” (G-4) -- Brazil, Germany, India and Japan, all of whom are aspiring to become permanent members of the Council -- would have the Assembly increase the Council’s membership from 15 to 25, by adding six permanent and four non-permanent members.
Another initiative considered by the Assembly was the African Union proposal, which would increase the body’s membership from 15 to 26, with increases in both the permanent and non-permanent categories, and granting Africa two permanent and five non-permanent seats.


Introduction of Draft

ALLAN ROCK (Canada), introducing the draft (document A/59/L.68), said that the objective of the text was to achieve the fairest and most democratic approach to the complex and controversial question of Security Council enlargement, while seeking the broadest possible consensus on how to proceed.  It would not serve the larger purpose if nations were left divided after choosing among resolutions that favoured a few, leaving fissures and factions as winners and losers were picked, once and for all.
The draft before the Assembly represented a good-faith effort to avoid such an “all or nothing” approach, he said.  It would add no permanent members to the Council, but would rather create new permanent seats in each region, leaving it to the members of each regional group to decide which Member States should sit in those seats, and for how long.  That approach would permit the international community to achieve all of the major objectives of Security Council reform, while preserving an environment conducive to broad agreement in September, and cooperation in the years ahead.
The accession of additional permanent members to the Council was not in the best interests of the United Nations, and it was not in the best interests of the overwhelming majority of its Member States, he continued.  Widening the permanent circle for the few who sought special status, no matter how worthy their candidacies, would make the Council less accountable for its conduct, more remote from the membership and less representative of the world’s regions.
His country favoured the approach presented in the draft, because it was democratic; it would make the Council more accountable to Member States; it provided for a flexible allocation of Council seats; and it provided for fairness.  And finally, it provided for a meaningful and effective Council reform without forcing divisive and potentially damaging votes on the General Assembly, as individual States vied for special status.
One of the aspects of the draft’s flexibility was that it allowed for repeated terms of different aggregate length among the elected seats permanently allocated to each region.  For example, it permanently accorded Africa six seats on the Council.  The African Group had made it clear that it wanted to have two representatives on the Council, who would be there for the long term.  The draft empowered the Group to identify two of its members who would represent the region for as long as that Group decided.  The balance of the seats set aside for Africa could be held for periods to be determined by the region.
Each of the other resolutions before the Assembly provided for new permanent members of the Council, but if either of those drafts were to be adopted, that would be only the beginning of a contentious and competitive process.  The approach of L.68 would entail a single initial vote of the Assembly, with subsequent elections that would implement the choices of regional groups.</text>
    </TextEngineInfo>
    <TextEngineInfo xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:type="textEngineInfo">
        <id>3</id>
        <intensity>0.17363778</intensity>
        <negativeGroup>divisive; fifteen; damaging; permanent; four; beginning; two; six; retiring; this; less; controversial; several; individual; once; following; africa; add; three; only; five; accountable; one; may; avoid; twenty; america; immediate; each; few; </negativeGroup>
        <polarity>POSITIVE</polarity>
        <positiveGroup>flexibility; ensure; serve; open; such; restraint; objective; call for; kingdom; competitive; formal; region; information; general; initiative; larger; text; great; eligible; fair; article; clear; council; security; group; member; contribution; american; major; flexible; represent; according; aspiring; membership; sit; continue; entail; republic; asian; united nations; length; social; first; country; increase; democratic; effective; due; allocation; election; worthy; term; rotation; identify; including; agreement; amend; determined; effort; have; international; rock; transparency; long; representative; affirmative; address; all; new; initial; matter; wanted; set aside; single; implement; assembly; permit; achieve; entitled; different; peace; over; balance; granting; proposal; addition; decide; contentious; draft; being; interested; participation; for; union; conducive; submit; require; better; western; additional; consensus; approach; create new; past; elect; circle; cooperation; circulation; adequate; exchange; left; subject; maintenance; majority; paragraph; question; regard; performance; environment; make; access; best; decision; interaction; remote; use; community; recommend; purpose; resolution; economic; vote; broad; meaningful; inclusive; possible; special; </positiveGroup>
        <text>The Security Council would consist of 20 elected members, serving for a two-year term, in addition to the five permanent members, according to a draft resolution presented to the General Assembly this afternoon.
By other terms of the text (document A/59/L.68), co-sponsored by the 12-strong group of Member States known as Uniting for Consensus, the Assembly would also make amendments to the United Nations Charter and submit them for ratification by Member States.  According to the text, the amended Article 23, paragraphs 1 and 2 of the Charter, would read, as follows:
“1.  The Security Council shall consist of twenty-five Members of the United Nations.  France, the People’s Republic of China, the Russian Federation, the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and the United States of America shall be permanent members of the Security Council.  The General Assembly shall elect twenty other members of the United Nations to be non-permanent members of the Security Council, due regard being specially paid, in the first instance, to the contribution of Members of the United Nations to the maintenance of international peace and security and to the other purposes of the Organization, and also to equitable geographical distribution.
“2.  The non-permanent members of the Security Council shall be elected for a term of two years.  In the first election of the non-permanent members after the increase of the membership of the Security Council from fifteen to twenty-five, five of the retiring members shall continue for one more year.  Non-permanent members may be eligible for immediate re-election, subject to the decision of their respective regional groups.”
Further by the text, the Assembly would also amend Article 27, paragraphs 2 and 3, and Article 109, paragraph 1, of the Charter to require the affirmative vote of 15 of the 25 Council members.  The Assembly would also call for improving the Council’s working methods in a transparent, inclusive and accountable manner, including restraint on the use of the veto; procedures to ensure transparency in decision-making, accountability in performance and access to information, including open briefings and interaction with all interested parties; consultation, cooperation and adequate exchange of information with the General Assembly and the Economic and Social Council; access and better participation of non-member States of the Security Council in its work; and the adoption and circulation of formal rules of procedure.


According to the text, presented to the Assembly by the representatives of four Uniting for Consensus members -- Canada, Italy, Colombia and Pakistan -- the Assembly would decide that the 20 non-permanent members of the Security Council would be elected according to the following pattern:  six from African States; five from Asian States; four from Latin American and Caribbean States; three from Western European and Other States; and two from Eastern European States.
The proposal would have the Assembly recommend that each geographical group decide on arrangements among its members for re-election or rotation of its members on the seats allotted to it.  Those arrangements would also address a fair subregional representation.
Other members and co-sponsors of the text, entitled “Reform of the Security Council”, are Argentina, Costa Rica, Malta, Mexico, Republic of Korea, San Marino, Spain and Turkey.
The text was introduced following discussions over the past two weeks on several competing proposals for Security Council reform.  The proposal by the “Group of Four” (G-4) -- Brazil, Germany, India and Japan, all of whom are aspiring to become permanent members of the Council -- would have the Assembly increase the Council’s membership from 15 to 25, by adding six permanent and four non-permanent members.
Another initiative considered by the Assembly was the African Union proposal, which would increase the body’s membership from 15 to 26, with increases in both the permanent and non-permanent categories, and granting Africa two permanent and five non-permanent seats.


Introduction of Draft

ALLAN ROCK (Canada), introducing the draft (document A/59/L.68), said that the objective of the text was to achieve the fairest and most democratic approach to the complex and controversial question of Security Council enlargement, while seeking the broadest possible consensus on how to proceed.  It would not serve the larger purpose if nations were left divided after choosing among resolutions that favoured a few, leaving fissures and factions as winners and losers were picked, once and for all.
The draft before the Assembly represented a good-faith effort to avoid such an “all or nothing” approach, he said.  It would add no permanent members to the Council, but would rather create new permanent seats in each region, leaving it to the members of each regional group to decide which Member States should sit in those seats, and for how long.  That approach would permit the international community to achieve all of the major objectives of Security Council reform, while preserving an environment conducive to broad agreement in September, and cooperation in the years ahead.
The accession of additional permanent members to the Council was not in the best interests of the United Nations, and it was not in the best interests of the overwhelming majority of its Member States, he continued.  Widening the permanent circle for the few who sought special status, no matter how worthy their candidacies, would make the Council less accountable for its conduct, more remote from the membership and less representative of the world’s regions.
His country favoured the approach presented in the draft, because it was democratic; it would make the Council more accountable to Member States; it provided for a flexible allocation of Council seats; and it provided for fairness.  And finally, it provided for a meaningful and effective Council reform without forcing divisive and potentially damaging votes on the General Assembly, as individual States vied for special status.
One of the aspects of the draft’s flexibility was that it allowed for repeated terms of different aggregate length among the elected seats permanently allocated to each region.  For example, it permanently accorded Africa six seats on the Council.  The African Group had made it clear that it wanted to have two representatives on the Council, who would be there for the long term.  The draft empowered the Group to identify two of its members who would represent the region for as long as that Group decided.  The balance of the seats set aside for Africa could be held for periods to be determined by the region.
Each of the other resolutions before the Assembly provided for new permanent members of the Council, but if either of those drafts were to be adopted, that would be only the beginning of a contentious and competitive process.  The approach of L.68 would entail a single initial vote of the Assembly, with subsequent elections that would implement the choices of regional groups.</text>
    </TextEngineInfo>
</texts>
